Guide to the Museum Studies Program Records RG.20.4
New York University Archives
Museum Studies Program Records
1975-2011
New York University Archives
New York University. Museum Studies Program
RG.20.4
9.74 Linear Feet in 18 manuscript boxes, 2 flat file folders, and 3 folders in 3 oversized shared boxes
New York University's Museum Studies Program is part of the Graduate School of Arts and Science. The program offers an interdisciplinary Master of Arts in Museum Studies and an Advanced Certificate in Museum Studies on the theory and practice of museum work, training its students in traditional museum disciplines such as research and writing, collecting and connoisseurship, registration and cataloging, and curatorial care for collections. This collection consists of materials created and collected by the Museum Studies Program between 1975 and 2011 documenting the program's internal administration, academic curriculum, sponsored events, and scholarly output. Materials include newspaper clippings, brochures, meeting agendas and minutes, memoranda and correspondence, and press releases.
Conditions Governing Access
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (materials in box 18). Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Tatiana Kamorina on behalf of the Museum Studies program in August 2018; the accession number associated with this transfer is 2018.002. In September 2019 an accretion was transferred by Program Administrator Candace Laning; the accession number associated with this gift is 2019.097.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into seven series. The series arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Governance
Series II. Administration
Series III. Courses
Series IV. Faculty and Staff
Series V. Grants, Fellowships, and Fundraising
Series VI. Publications
Series VII. Events and Publicity
Each series is arranged chronologically except for series VI, which is arranged alphabetically.
Historical Note
Since 1978, the Program in Museum Studies at New York University has offered a course of interdisciplinary study in the contemporary theory and practice of museum work. As part of the Graduate School of Arts and Science, students receive a broad foundation in the history and theory of museums, the creation and maintenance of exhibitions and collections, and museum management. They also pursue personal programs of study supporting individual academic and career objectives. Faculty are specialized in various academic fields whose work engages museum theory and practice, and students are trained to perform a variety of roles within all types of museums. The Museum Studies Program offers a Master of Arts degree in Museum Studies; an Advanced Certificate in Museum Studies; and a Concentration in Museum Studies to those enrolled for a Master's degree in Africana Studies, Hebrew and Judaic Studies, Latin American and Caribbean Studies, and Near Eastern Studies. Dr. Flora S. Kaplan was the program's founding director from 1978 through 1999, and continued her involvement as Professor Emerita until her passing in 2021.
Source Cited:
"Graduate Program in Museum Studies." Graduate Program, Program in Museum Studies, accessed August 29, 2024, https://as.nyu.edu/departments/museumstudies/graduate.html.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created and collected by New York University's program in Museum Studies between 1975-2011, documenting the program's internal administration, academic curriculum, sponsored events, and scholarly output. Materials include newspaper clippings, brochures describing the academic program, meeting agenda and minutes, memoranda and correspondence regarding student admissions and internships, press releases announcing sponsored events and publications by faculty, course syllabi, and memoranda and correspondence concerning NYU's Faculty of Arts and Science. This collection also includes materials documenting the program's administrative operations, including reports, correspondence, and memoranda regarding budgets, financial aid, personnel, and grant-funding.
Museum techniques; Museums -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Museums -- Educational aspects; Education, Higher -- United States.
- Series I. Governance, 1976-2008; 2.19 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials related to the governing bodies of the Museum Studies Program. These materials include meeting minutes of the Steering Committee and other committees and task forces (such as the AAM Museum Studies Committee and Humanities Council). Also included are decisions on curriculum changes and degree requirements, self-studies, and reports (including reports from other divisions and committees). These items illustrate changes in the requirements of the program and the creation of the certificate and concentration program.
  - Steering Committee, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Steering Committee, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Steering Committee, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Steering Committee, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Steering Committee, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Museum Studies Advisory Committee, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Humanities Council, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7, Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Museums -- Museum Studies Task Force, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1977-1998
    - Center for Latin American and Caribbean Studies Annual Reports, 1977-1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - New York University Annual Reports and Enrollment Reports, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Museum Studies Self-Study, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Registration of Historical Collections of the National Park Service, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Registration of Archival Collections of the National Park Service, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art -- "Minority Art Professionals in Northeastern and Mid-Atlantic States: An Exploratory Study of Their Problems and Needs", 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Interim Report of the University-Wide Planning Commission, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Commission on Graduate Priorities, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Museum Studies Program Planning, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Museum Studies Program Self-Study, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Master of Arts in Museum Studies, 1976-2008
    - Degree Requirements and Changes, 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Degree Requirements and Changes, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Degree Requirements and Changes, 1990-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Degree Requirements and Changes, 2000-2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Degree Requirements and Changes, 2004-2008 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Materials in this folder are closed for 20 years from the latest date.
    - Master of Arts Programs with Concentrations in Museum Studies, 1983-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    - Requirements at Other Institutions, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series II. Administration, 1978-2007; 2.92 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, 2 flat file folders, and 2 folder in 2 shared oversized boxes
  This series contains materials related to the daily operations of the Museum Studies Program. These materials include admission and financial aid manuals, budgets, registration and enrollment statistics, student orientation information, general correspondence (regarding admissions and internships), and Peterson's guide submissions.
  - Administrative Assistant -- Memos and Job Responsibilities, 1981-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Admissions and Financial Aid, 1980-1998 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Advertisements for the Museum Studies Program, 1982-1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Budgets, 1978-1997 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Peterson's Guides, 1981-1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Space, 1979-1998
    - Blueprints, 1980 (Flat-file-folder Temp 001, Box Shared University Archives 150, Folder 6)
    - Blueprint Sketches, circa 1980 (Box Shared University Archives 097, Folder 19)
    - Memos and Correspondence, 1979-1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Statistics, 1978-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Students, 1979-1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - General Program Correspondence, circa 1978-1983 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - General Program Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - General Program Correspondence, 1988-1994 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - General Program Correspondence, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - General Program Correspondence, 1996-2003 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - General Program Correspondence, 2007 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Series III. Courses, 1975-2011; 2.38 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 1 flat file folder, and 1 folder in an oversized shared box
  This series consists of materials related to classes and seminars offered by the Museum Studies Program. Also included are materials related to the internship requirement. Materials include syllabi, course materials, internship guidelines, lists of participating internship organizations, and assigned reading materials.
  - Intro to Museum Studies and Museology -- Department of Anthropology, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Museum Studies Summer and Fall Semesters, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Museum Studies Fall Semester, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Museum Studies Summer and Fall Semesters, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1987
    - Syllabi, Course Listings, and Readings (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Summer Course Poster (Box Shared University Archives 150, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Museum Studies Fall Semester, 1989
    - Syllabi, Course Listings, and Readings (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Cooperative Education and Museum Training Program with New York Transit Museum -- Class Posters (Box Shared University Archives 150, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Museum Studies Fall Semester, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Summer Semesters, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Museum Studies Fall Semester, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Museum Studies Summer and Fall Semesters, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Museum Studies Summer and Fall Semesters, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Spring, Summer, and Fall Semesters, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Museum Studies Spring Semester, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2010 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Museum Studies Spring and Fall Semesters, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Masters of Arts in Liberal Studies Courses, 1992-1996 (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Series IV. Faculty and Staff, 1978-2004; 2.19 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes
  This series includes materials related to the faculty, deans, directors, and other staff members, of the Museum Studies Program. These materials reflect the relationships between the director, faculty, and staff of the Museum Studies Program with various deans, heads of divisions, and other administrative departments. Materials consist of correspondence and memos, meeting minutes, reports, faculty lists, publications by various faculty members, awards received by various faculty members, and handbooks.
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence and Memos, 1978-1987 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence, Memos, and Data Book, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence and Memos, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence and Memos, 1992-1994 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence, Memos, and Proposal, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence and Memos, 1997-1998 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence and Memos, 1999-2001 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Faculty, Chairs, and Heads of Departments -- Correspondence, 2004 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Center for Latin American and Caribbean Studies Faculty -- Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1980-1994 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Council of Arts and Science Chairs -- Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1987-1998 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Directors of Graduate Studies -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1978-1998 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science -- Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science -- Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1986-1989 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Museum Studies Faculty -- Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science and Museum Studies Faculty -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science and Museum Studies Faculty -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, Handbook, and Reports, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Museum Studies Faculty -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Faculty of Arts and Science -- Meeting Minutes, Agendas, and Reports, 1997-1998 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Graduate Curriculum Committee -- Memos and Reports, 1979, 1988-1998 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Series V. Grants, Fellowships, and Fundraising, 1978-2005; 1.31 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes
  This series describes fundraising activities for the Museum Studies Program. Materials consist of grant applications and reports, fellowship applications, funding opportunities from other university divisions and departments, and grant applications from other institutions.
  - Fellowship and Scholarship Opportunities, 1978-1997 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "Training of Minority and Third World Museum Professionals" Grant, 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - The Living Brain Traveling Exhibition -- Grant Proposal, 1995-1996 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Grant for "Guardians of Monuments and Memory: Case Studies in Urban Conservation and Museums in the Middle East" Conference, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Grants and Fundraising -- General, 1978-1996 (Box 14, Folder 8-9, Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Grants and Fundraising -- General, 2005 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Series VI. Publications, 1978-2000; 1.13 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and 1 folder in a shared oversized box
  This series consists of publications created by the Museum Studies Program. These materials include drafts and final published versions of brochures, course catalogs, a working paper series from the faculty, and a department newsletter. Also included are brochures and newsletters of the Master of Arts programs with Museum Studies concentrations.
  - Brochures, circa 1978-2000 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
  - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Bulletin -- Museum Studies Program Copy, 1990-2000 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Museum Studies Newsletter, 1980-1987 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Museum Studies Newsletter, 1988-1996 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Museum Studies Newsletter, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Museum Studies Newsletter, 1998-1999 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Poster, 1982 (Box Shared University Archives 147, Folder 15)
  - Website Text, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Working Papers Series, 1987-1994 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - MA in Hebrew and Judaic Studies with Concentration in Museum Studies -- Brochures and Bulletin Copy, 1988-1997 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - MA in Latin American and Caribbean Studies with a Concentration in Museum Studies -- Brochures and Newsletters, 1981-1995 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - MA in Near Eastern Studies with a Concentration in Museum Studies -- Brochures, Newsletters, and Bulletins, circa 1984-1993 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Series VII. Events and Publicity, 1980-1999; 1.31 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 flat file folder, and 2 folders in 2 shared oversized boxes
  This series consists of materials related to the Musuem Studies Program's sponsored events and related publicity. Events include exhibitions, conferences, lectures, and symposia. Materials include event brochures, posters, newspaper clippings, photographs, correspondence with participants, and invitations.
  - Images of Power: Art of the Royal Court of Benin Exhibition, 1980-1982 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - "Put Your Best Face Forward: Public Relations and Institutional Development" Symposium, 1981-1982 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - "Museums and National Identity: The Importance of Objects in the Formation of the Nation-State" Lecture Series, 1987-1988
    - Grant Proposal, Press Release, Introductory Remarks, and Lecture Transcript, 1987-1988 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Poster, 1987 (Box Shared University Archives 147, Folder 15)
  - "Queens, Queen Mothers, Priestesses, and Power: Case Studies in African Gender" Conference, 1988-1991
    - Correspondence and Report, 1988-1991 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Poster, 1991 (Box Shared University Archives 147, Folder 15)
  - 15th Anniversary of the Museum Studies Program, 1992-1993 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - "Culture/Crafts, Museums/Markets: Mexican Artists in the Global Market" Conference, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - "Guardians of Monuments and Memory: Case Studies in Urban Conservation and Museums in the Middle East" Conference, 1997-1998 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - 20th Anniversary of the Museum Studies Program Poster, 1998 (Box Shared University Archives 150, Folder 6)
  - Events and Publicity -- General, 1980-1999 (Box 17, Folder 2-3)